<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Canterbury Christmas or, a true relation of the insurrection in Canterbury on Christmas day last, with the great hurt that befell divers persons thereby. / Written by a Cittizen there, to his friend in London.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79894</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E421_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204765</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864227</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864227</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161372</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79894)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161372)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 66:E421[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Canterbury Christmas or, a true relation of the insurrection in Canterbury on Christmas day last, with the great hurt that befell divers persons thereby. / Written by a Cittizen there, to his friend in London.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 4, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Harward,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "Jan: 1st", "1647", the "8" in the imprint has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christmas --  England --  Canterbury --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Canterbury (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161372:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CANTERBVRY CHRISTMAS: OR, A True Relation of the Inſurrection in <hi>CANTERB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY</hi> on <hi>Chriſtmas day</hi> laſt, with the great hurt that befell divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by a Cittizen there, to his friend in</hi> London.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Harward.</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:161372:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161372:2"/>
            <head>CANTERBVRY CHRISTMAS: OR, A True Relation of the Inſurrection in <hi>Canterbury</hi> on <hi>Chriſtmas Day</hi> laſt, with the great hurt that befell divers perſons thereby.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon Wedneſday, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 22. the Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>Canterbury</hi> by the appointment of Maſter <hi>Major,</hi> openly proclaimed, that Chriſtmas day, and all other Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Feſtivals ſhould be put downe, and that a Market ſhould be kept upon <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which being not obſerved, (but very ill taken by the Country) the towne was thereby unſerved with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion &amp; trading very much hindered; which occaſioned great diſcontent among the people, cauſed them to riſe in a Rebellious way.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> being ſlighted, &amp; his Commands obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (only of a few) who opened their Shops, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of 12 at the moſt: They were commanded by the multitude to ſhut up again, but refuſing to obey, their ware was thrown up and down, and they at laſt forced to ſhut in.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:161372:3"/>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> and his aſſiſtants uſed their beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to qualifie the tumult, but the fire-being once kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, was not eaſily quenched.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sheriffe</hi> laying hold of a fellow, was ſtoutly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted; which the <hi>Major</hi> perceiving, took a Cudgell, and ſtrook the man: who being: now puny, pulled up his ſpirit, and knockt down the <hi>Major,</hi> whereby his Cloak was much torne and durty, beſides the hurt he received.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> hereupon made ſtrict Proclamation for keeping the Peace, and that every man depart to his own houſe.</p>
            <p>The multitude hollowing thereat, in diſorderly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; the <hi>Aldermen</hi> and <hi>Conſtables</hi> caught two or three of the rout, and ſent them to the Jaile, but they ſoon broke looſe, and Jeered Maſter <hi>Alderman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soone after iſſued forth the Commanders of this Rabble, with an addition of Souldiers into the high ſtreet, and brought with them two Foot-bales, whereby their company increaſed. Which the <hi>Major</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen</hi> perceiving took what priſoners they had got, and would have carried them to the Jayle. But the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude following after to the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> were oppoſed by Captain <hi>Bridg,</hi> who was ſtraight knockt down and had his head broke in two places, not being able to withſtand the multitude, who getting betwixt him and the Jayle, reſcued their fellowes, and beat the <hi>Major</hi> and <hi>Aldermen</hi> into their houſes, and then cried <hi>conqueſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where leaving them to breath a while, they went to one <hi>Whites</hi> a Barber, (a man noted to be a buſie fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low) whoſe windowes they pulled downe to the ground: The like they did to divers others, till night over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161372:3"/>them, and they were forced to depart, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing peaceable the next day, it being the Saboth.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Munday</hi> morning the Multitude comming, the <hi>Major</hi> ſet a ſtrong watch with Muskers and Holbards in the City, both at the Gates and at S. <hi>Andrews</hi> Church, the Captaine of the Guard was <hi>White</hi> the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <p>Till noon they were quiet, <hi>then</hi> came one <hi>Joyce</hi> a Hackney man, whom <hi>White</hi> bid ſtand, the fellow asked what the matter was, and withall called him Round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head; whereat <hi>White</hi> being moved, cocked his Piſtoll and would have ſhot him, but the <hi>Major</hi> wiſht him to hold: Nevertheleſſe he ſhot, and the fellow fell down but was not dead. Whence aroſe a ſunden clamour that a man was murdered, whereupon the people came forth with clubs, The <hi>Major</hi> and <hi>Aldermen</hi> made haſte away; the Towne Roſe againe and the Country came in, took poſſeſſion of the Gates, and made enquiry for <hi>White,</hi> they found him in a hay-loft, where they broke his head, and drag'd him in the ſtreets, ſetting open the Priſon dores and releaſing thoſe that were in hold.</p>
            <p>Next they vowed revenge on the <hi>Major,</hi> pulling up his poſts, breaking his windowes, but at laſt, being perſwaded by Sir <hi>William Man,</hi> Maſter <hi>Loveliſe,</hi> Maſter <hi>Harris,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Purſer</hi> had much a doe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them from taking of his Perſon; ſo came tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly into the high ſtreet, and their demands were ſo high, that thoſe Gentlemen could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them. Afterward meeting Maſter <hi>Burly</hi> the Town Clark, demanded the Keyes of the Priſon from him, which being granted, they with thoſe Gentlemen formerly named, went again to the Town Hall to Treat,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161372:4"/>and came to an agreement, which was, that forty or fifty of their own men ſhould keep the Town that night, being compleatly armed, which being performed (the morning iſſued) and they continued in arms till Tueſday morning: There are none as yet dead, but diverſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly hurt.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Sheriffe</hi> taking <hi>Whites</hi> part, and ſtriving to keep the Peace, was knockt down, and his head fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully broke, it was Gods mercy his braines were not beat out, but it ſhould ſeeme he had a clung pate of own.</p>
            <p>They went alſo without S. <hi>Georges</hi>-gate, and did much injury to M. <hi>Lee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As I am credibly informed, the injuries that are done are theſe.</p>
            <p>They have beat down all the windowes of M. <hi>Majors</hi> Houſe, burnt the Stoups at the comming in of his dore. Maſter <hi>Reeves</hi> windowes were broke. Maſter <hi>Page,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Pollen,</hi> one <hi>Buchurſt,</hi> Captaine <hi>Bridge, Thomas Harris,</hi> a buſie prating fellow, and others were ſorely wounded.</p>
            <p>It is Ordered, that <hi>Richard White</hi> and <hi>Robert Hues,</hi> being in fetters, be tryed according to the Law, and upon faire Compoſition, the multitude have delivered their Armes into the Hands of the City, upon engagements of the beſt of the City, that no man ſhall further queſtion or trouble them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
